This material is made available to you by or on
NOTE CONF
behalf of the University of Melbourne under section 113P of
the Copyright Act 1968.
NOTE CONF
It may be subject to copyright.
For more information, visit the university copyright website.
NOTE CONF
Exactly.
OK, uh, good morning.
NOTE CONF
I hope that uh It's all pretty clear to everybody
what's gonna happen this week in terms of the quizzes.
NOTE CONF
Yeah, there have been some questions and I've been answering
them on the discussion thread, so, Um, hopefully be pretty
NOTE CONF
clear what kinds of questions you're gonna be asked and
how the, uh, quiz is gonna be run.
NOTE CONF
Uh, for those of you Who here is a Tuesday
5 to 7?
NOTE CONF
OK.
Um, for the Tuesday, 5:00 p.m. to 7:00 p.m., nothing
NOTE CONF
changes this week, but we have opened a second room.
Uh, so this week, uh, you regularly get, uh, Mazino
NOTE CONF
as your tutor.
Uh, so Amir will also come, uh, this week, so
NOTE CONF
you'll have two tutors, and, uh, the tutors will Agree
on how which groups will stay and which groups will
NOTE CONF
move to the new room, right?
So, we're trying to reduce the numbers because some classes
NOTE CONF
have a lot of numbers.
So there will be new, new tutorials set up, uh,
NOTE CONF
starting next week, uh, and you'll get the directions in
that class.
NOTE CONF
If you want to move to that class, if you
are free Tuesday, 5 to 7.
NOTE CONF
And you want to move to that class anyway because
your classroom is overfilled, then please do message me and
NOTE CONF
I'll ask the tutors to, I'll find out from the
tutors how much space there is once today is done.
NOTE CONF
OK.
So, uh, this week, we're going to talk about, um,
NOTE CONF
we're going to Somebody's forgotten to, sorry.
Um, we're gonna, we're gonna introduce the four types of
NOTE CONF
management controls that, uh, we will do deep dives in
over the next, uh, well, not next week, but the
NOTE CONF
4 weeks after that.
And that is, uh, risk, policy, strategy, and CETA.
NOTE CONF
CETA stands for Security, Education, Training and Awareness.
Um, but before we get there, we're going to, uh,
NOTE CONF
sort of do a bit of a recap to try
to, um, get a feel for what the big picture
NOTE CONF
is before we start to focus on those four.
Let me start with today's maxim, today's, uh, statement.
NOTE CONF
Security is a process, not a product.
OK.
NOTE CONF
So, um, Who thinks they, oh, I might just ask
you directly, why is security a process, not a product?
NOTE CONF
Do you have to explain that on the exam?
10 marks For an explanation, why is security a process,
NOTE CONF
not a product?
What would be your answer?
NOTE CONF
Application that is secure something.
Keep up with Train everyone to actually get to the
NOTE CONF
point.
So you can't a single application cannot secure everything.
NOTE CONF
You need to.
Train people.
NOTE CONF
Uh, have good practices and have good have good practices,
OK.
NOTE CONF
Interesting.
How many marks would I give for that?
NOTE CONF
I don't know.
I don't have a rubric at the back of my
NOTE CONF
mind, but yeah, interesting, uh, point and definitely relevant.
Any other?
NOTE CONF
Who thinks security is a product?
You have an inherent.
NOTE CONF
Disagreement with that, you may not be able to explain
it, but you feel that it's wrong.
NOTE CONF
Right.
Who thinks security, who believes that security can be a
NOTE CONF
product.
How?
NOTE CONF
Yeah, I mean some companies.
Some are you sell security yeah.
NOTE CONF
of And by physicians.
Yeah, so people sell security, but what are they selling?
NOTE CONF
I think security is uh operation.
Project but they some companies send solutions and some sell
NOTE CONF
services and some simple.
Security is an operation, not a product, and some companies
NOTE CONF
sell services, some sell products, solutions, etc.
etc.
NOTE CONF
OK.
So, um, I think maybe the, the easiest way to
NOTE CONF
understand this is think about home security and think about
a padlock on your gate or the lock on your
NOTE CONF
front door.
Is the lock security.
NOTE CONF
Is security, is this home, is the security of your
home, the lock, or the padlock, or the door?
NOTE CONF
The, the heavy, you know, 16-inch steel gauge door, is
that, is that your security?
NOTE CONF
No, right?
It's obvious that it's not, that it's part of the,
NOTE CONF
part of your security, but it's not your security as
a whole.
NOTE CONF
And in fact, there is no product that you could
buy for your home that could Assure Security for you.
NOTE CONF
There is no single product.
Right?
NOTE CONF
So when you want to set up security in your
home, let's say you just, you know, built your brand
NOTE CONF
new, brand spanking new home, and you're really happy to
get into it, and you want to set up security,
NOTE CONF
who do you call?
You call a locksmith to give you advice on how
NOTE CONF
to set up your security?
You call a CCTV company to install cameras to give
NOTE CONF
you advice.
Who do you call?
NOTE CONF
Nobody's a homeowner here.
You haven't thought about it, OK, you don't have to,
NOTE CONF
but I mean just think logically.
Some of you are probably renting a property, yeah, at
NOTE CONF
least living.
Who here is not living with your parents?
NOTE CONF
OK.
So, some autonomy on your, on your personal situation, yeah.
NOTE CONF
Who did you call?
You probably didn't call anybody.
NOTE CONF
You probably haven't thought about security very often, yeah.
But for sure, you don't have anybody in the market
NOTE CONF
that you can call to give you advice on security,
specifically, right?
NOTE CONF
There is no market.
Service provider whose entire job is to vendor independent, give
NOTE CONF
you advice on security, on how to set up your
home security.
NOTE CONF
That does not exist.
As far as I know, there isn't, right?
NOTE CONF
You can call an alarm company, you can call a
camera company, call a locksmith, and they'll give you plenty
NOTE CONF
of advice, but they're not, they're not strategists.
They are product centric people.
NOTE CONF
Because there is no market for strategy, because people don't
value it.
NOTE CONF
Right?
They just put in the, the, everybody just ticks a
NOTE CONF
list of boxes and says, I need a lock on
my front door.
NOTE CONF
I might want an alarm system, I want cameras, but
there's nobody who's coming to you saying, hold on, before
NOTE CONF
you install cameras and locks and doors and windows, blah
blah, let's first figure out what your assets are, what
NOTE CONF
do you have in your home that you need to
protect, um, that's valuable.
NOTE CONF
Aside from you, yourself.
And do you, is there somebody specific that you're worried
NOTE CONF
about that's gonna come at you?
Um, is that a, is that a nation state?
NOTE CONF
Is it ASIO?
Uh, or is it police, uh, people you don't trust
NOTE CONF
in the police, or is it your cousin, or is
it the neighborhood burglar, or is it an assassin?
NOTE CONF
Like, who is it?
Because the who It's gonna, that's gonna come after you
NOTE CONF
is more important than any other question, right?
If you don't have anybody specific in mind and it's
NOTE CONF
just your neighborhood burglar, then we can install controls and
equipment that is designed, you know, that's, that's basically priced
NOTE CONF
at that point, right?
It'll deter any neighborhood burglar, but if you're worried about
NOTE CONF
the government, then that is an entirely different bar and
your expenditure is gonna go through the roof.
NOTE CONF
You see what I mean?
So it's not the product.
NOTE CONF
It's the process of finding out what kind of security
do you need, what are you protecting, who are you
NOTE CONF
going to protect against, where is the bar you need
to set, and how much can you invest to be
NOTE CONF
able to control the uncertainty of what might happen to
you.
NOTE CONF
So that is a process.
It's a learning process.
NOTE CONF
If you have numbers of incidents happening to you, then
you learn about what's working and what's not, and you
NOTE CONF
fix it and refine it.
That is a process.
NOTE CONF
It's not a product.
OK.
NOTE CONF
So, this week, uh, module 4, no prescribed reading.
For those of you who are reading the textbook, you
NOTE CONF
have a free week.
Um, discussion boards are open for your conversations, and of
NOTE CONF
course, a lot of the activity will be in the
workshop where you'll have Q&A, you'll have a quiz this
NOTE CONF
week, um, and no, it will not be at the
beginning of the of the tutorial, it'll be towards the
NOTE CONF
end of it, just to make sure everybody stays.
Uh, and then there'll be the horizon case, and then
NOTE CONF
there'll be a special case, uh, which, uh, is a
one-page case scenario, uh, which is again going to give
NOTE CONF
you more practice for your exam.
If we have time today, I'll show you the scenario,
NOTE CONF
might talk through it, but definitely you'll have time in
the, in the workshop to do it.
NOTE CONF
So, I want to talk about risk management and talk
about the triplet model again, just to remind you, security
NOTE CONF
has two ingredients, an asset and a threat.
Something worth protecting, something you're protecting the asset from, and
NOTE CONF
without those two, you can't have a security problem.
And as we said before, when you have, for every
NOTE CONF
specific asset, And for every specific threat actor.
And every specific vulnerability in the system that's protecting the
NOTE CONF
asset or the asset itself, there is a combination specific
asset paired with a specific threat actor paired with specific
NOTE CONF
vulnerability creates a unique scenario which is a risk, and
there are a lot of scenarios usually in any organization.
NOTE CONF
Those scenarios collectively are your risk exposure, and in order
to control or reduce your risk exposure, you bring in
NOTE CONF
these formal, informal, and technological controls, and they should work
in combination.
NOTE CONF
They should be aligned to each other to try to
work collectively to reduce your risk.
NOTE CONF
And your major constraints are you cannot bring your risk
down to zero.
NOTE CONF
It's impossible.
You do not have unlimited resources.
NOTE CONF
So it always becomes a decision about how much you
can invest in security to reduce uncertainty as much as
NOTE CONF
possible.
The goal is control.
NOTE CONF
I need to control my situation.
I need to make it predictable and consistently.
NOTE CONF
I need to be.
A consistent situation as much as possible and a predictable
NOTE CONF
one so I know what might happen and what controls
are in place to deal with those uncertainties.
NOTE CONF
Once I have control, I have that sense of balance
that is security.
NOTE CONF
Security is a sense of assurance that we have that
our risk and our controls are in balance.
NOTE CONF
You cannot have perfect security in the sense that there's
no risk.
NOTE CONF
You have to live with risk, you have to learn
to live with risk, and controlled risk is the best
NOTE CONF
we can do, right?
So that's, that's our goal, controlled risk.
NOTE CONF
So, At the end of the day we will have
a portfolio of risk scenarios, and our aim is to
NOTE CONF
come to that controlled risk situation, but we haven't answered
the main question, which is we might have identified a
NOTE CONF
range of risk scenarios.
There might be 1000, 10,000, 100,000 risk scenarios.
NOTE CONF
Now what?
We've just said generally we need to control the risk,
NOTE CONF
but how do we control risk?
And so in modern day security, risk management is the
NOTE CONF
key paradigm we use to try to control risk, and
what that means is once you've identified all the scenarios,
NOTE CONF
the first thing you do is you estimate the likelihood
of each scenario.
NOTE CONF
What is the likelihood that this scenario is going to
happen?
NOTE CONF
And then we estimate.
The impact.
NOTE CONF
If this scenario happened, what would be the estimated dollar
amount that this would cost us as an organization?
NOTE CONF
And we usually use qualitative, not quantitative.
Metrics.
NOTE CONF
So we decide what is low, what is medium, and
what is high for both probability and impact.
NOTE CONF
And low could mean once a year, medium could be
once a month, high could be once a week or
NOTE CONF
once a day.
It doesn't really matter.
NOTE CONF
What the graduations are as long as we are consistent
in using the same yardstick for all the scenarios.
NOTE CONF
So we estimate probability in terms of frequency of an
event happening on a calendar year and impact.
NOTE CONF
And impact is really hard to measure.
We're going to talk a lot about it when we
NOTE CONF
get to the week on risk, but impact is usually
around dollars, and it's very difficult to quantify, but there
NOTE CONF
are a lot of factors, and impact is reputation.
There's, you know, trademark value.
NOTE CONF
There is, you know, the.
Of your lawyers, your, your people, productivity losses, trust, and
NOTE CONF
all these things somebody needs to put a dollar value
on at some stage.
NOTE CONF
But at the end of this exercise, we have a
probability indicator and an impact indicator for each scenario.
NOTE CONF
And once we have those indicators, all we need to
do then is to sort all the scenarios so the
NOTE CONF
scenarios with the highest probability and highest impact go to
the top and the lowest probability and lowest impact go
NOTE CONF
to the bottom, and it's easy to do.
You just say low is 1, medium is 2, high
NOTE CONF
is 3, and you just multiply them out.
So high impact, high probability 3 times 3 is 9.
NOTE CONF
It's going to go to the top.
Low probability, low impact 1 times 1 is 1.
NOTE CONF
It's going to go to the bottom.
Sort from the highest to the lowest.
NOTE CONF
All the 9s go to the top, all the 1s
go to the bottom, and you have a mix in
NOTE CONF
between, and that is your risk assessment.
It's a criticality assessment.
NOTE CONF
So you have a sorted list of all the scenarios
by criticality in your organization, and that concludes the risk
NOTE CONF
assessment.
And then you go to your risk response.
NOTE CONF
You say, OK, I've got 1000 different scenarios, sorted from
high criticality to low criticality, what's my risk appetite?
NOTE CONF
Right?
At what point will I just simply accept and do
NOTE CONF
nothing about a risk scenario, yep, it can happen, if
it happens, it happens, I'll take the impact.
NOTE CONF
You just draw a line and say maybe everything from
4 and below I'll accept, but everything above 4, I
NOTE CONF
won't, or 5 or 6, it's up to you.
But the appetite is basically what will I accept.
NOTE CONF
So you have these options, I, you can accept the
risk, which means you do nothing about it.
NOTE CONF
You can avoid the risk.
And you might say, how can I avoid the risk
NOTE CONF
if it's a scenario that's realistic and plausible, and the
way is you can re-engineer or reorganize or change your
NOTE CONF
organization situation so the risk never occurs, right?
So for example, if the risk is around a document.
NOTE CONF
You've got a document, it's, it's, uh, you know, it's
got valuable information.
NOTE CONF
If it leaked, it would have a huge impact.
You might ask, do I still need the document?
NOTE CONF
Maybe it's a legacy document.
Maybe the documents created 5 years ago, and it's still
NOTE CONF
hanging around, it would still have impact because it's got
all these credit card numbers or whatever, but I can
NOTE CONF
delete it.
I don't need it anymore.
NOTE CONF
If you deleted the asset, you avoided the risk, right?
No scenario can come up if the asset does not
NOTE CONF
exist.
Simple.
NOTE CONF
Right, so that's a risk avoidance example.
You can re-engineer things.
NOTE CONF
So if there's a risk is about, you know, getting
a message that could, that could leak through WhatsApp, don't
NOTE CONF
use WhatsApp.
Maybe you can assess that Signal is more secure.
NOTE CONF
Then maybe you can remove some risk scenarios by shifting
from WhatsApp to Signal or to SMS, right?
NOTE CONF
So the point is you change the architecture of the
technology or the choices that you make changes the risk
NOTE CONF
profile.
You may remove certain risk scenarios, might introduce new ones,
NOTE CONF
but you can certainly remove risk scenarios, and that's called
risk avoidance.
NOTE CONF
The 3rd is risk transfer.
So you may decide to outsource something that was your
NOTE CONF
responsibility, and by outsourcing it, you have transferred the risk
to the outsourced party.
NOTE CONF
It's now their problem, not your problem.
And you've got mitigation, which is if the scenario happened,
NOTE CONF
you don't put anything to prevent it, but if it
did happen, then the outcome or the impact is controlled.
NOTE CONF
So for example, incident response is a great example.
You might have an incident, yes, you have preventive controls,
NOTE CONF
but you also have an incident response of crisis management
team.
NOTE CONF
They're there to mitigate the impact.
Right, to not allow the impact to be full blown
NOTE CONF
and uncontrolled, but to control the impact, and that's called
risk mitigation.
NOTE CONF
And at the end of this whole exercise of deciding
what you're going to mitigate, what you're going to accept,
NOTE CONF
what you're going to avoid.
You then have to do a risk review, which is
NOTE CONF
to to accept that the, the risk identification exercise that
you went through.
NOTE CONF
Identified maybe 1000 scenarios, but tomorrow there will be new
scenarios.
NOTE CONF
Right.
Next week, there'll be new scenarios, next month, there'll be
NOTE CONF
new, so it is a changing, the risk environment is
constantly in flux, it's constantly changing, so you need to
NOTE CONF
review your risks and update it very often.
OK.
NOTE CONF
Very quickly, The regional security manager for LegalCo is staring
out her large floor to ceiling window overlooking the park.
NOTE CONF
She notices that Jim is sitting on a bench frantically
typing on his laptop.
NOTE CONF
He must be working on the pricing strategy for tomorrow's
tender proposal.
NOTE CONF
A young woman stops a few meters away and appears
interested in his screen.
NOTE CONF
Fiona freezes.
She recognizes her as an employee of a competitor across
NOTE CONF
the street.
She grabs her handbag and heads for the park.
NOTE CONF
So regional security manager for a legal company staring out
her window overlooking the park, he notices a colleague sitting
NOTE CONF
on a bench working on a sensitive document, and a
young woman who is working at a competing legal firm
NOTE CONF
is in visual.
You know, range She runs out to the park to
NOTE CONF
try to do the obvious, so the question is, what's
the asset?
NOTE CONF
The the pricing strategy.
Yeah, OK.
NOTE CONF
Tender proposal, you could argue.
The pricing strategy, tender proposal, yeah.
NOTE CONF
The document that he's working on.
What's the threat?
NOTE CONF
The young woman is a threat actor.
He's not the threat.
NOTE CONF
Speak up, sorry.
So the theft or the leakage of it is the
NOTE CONF
threat.
The danger here is that there be a leak or
NOTE CONF
a theft of that.
What's the vulnerability?
NOTE CONF
Sorry?
Shoulder surfing.
NOTE CONF
Shoulder surfing, I would say maybe is the tactic or
the mechanism, but what's the vulnerability?
NOTE CONF
Exactly uncontrolled environments where it could be stolen, that is
a vulnerability.
NOTE CONF
This person should be working in a controlled, secured environment,
but he's working on it out in the park where
NOTE CONF
anybody could just show up and look at it, right?
So there's an uncontrolled environment within which a sensitive document
NOTE CONF
is being manipulated or is being worked on, and so
the vulnerability is that uncontrolled environment.
NOTE CONF
So what's the scenario?
If Right here For uh Tender proposal, yeah, the tender,
NOTE CONF
yeah, yeah, yeah, OK, so I mean what you wanna
do when you're asked what's the risk is to have
NOTE CONF
the full scenario.
You have to make sure that all the ingredients are
NOTE CONF
there, so you've got the employee of a competitor.
Who May be able to, or a specific competitor, not
NOTE CONF
any competitor, we don't tell you what it is, but
in an exam question, we would.
NOTE CONF
So, let's say it's called ABC.
So the, the employee of ABC may be able to
NOTE CONF
View or steal.
The tendered for the pricing strategy.
NOTE CONF
From Jim's particular asset, right, which is the laptop.
So, you've got the threat actor, you've got the asset,
NOTE CONF
you've got the vulnerability, the specific, not the generic.
None of these are generic.
NOTE CONF
You have a very specific threat actor, you have a
very specific document.
NOTE CONF
Right?
So that the very specific asset, very specific threat actor,
NOTE CONF
and very specific pathway, which is the, the uncontrolled environment
is being used to visually steal the actual document.
NOTE CONF
So if that young lady came up and grabbed the
laptop and ran, that's a different scenario.
NOTE CONF
Right?
A different scenario.
NOTE CONF
If she went to Jim and asked him a question
about the pricing strategy, and Jim told her, that's a
NOTE CONF
different scenario.
Now you might think, no, they're the same, they're all
NOTE CONF
about the document being leaked, but no, they're not, because
you think about the controls, to stop Jim from telling
NOTE CONF
this young lady would require behavioral training.
To stop the laptop from being stolen, right, and used
NOTE CONF
would require maybe encryption on the device.
To stop the visual range, you would need a device
NOTE CONF
that you would have to be looking straight on.
To protect and cannot be stolen or cannot be viewed
NOTE CONF
from the side, or even better, you would have training
that individuals working on this particular document cannot leave the
NOTE CONF
premises, right?
So the controls are different depending on the risk scenario,
NOTE CONF
and even though they're all involve the young lady and
the assets, the same asset, the same young lady.
NOTE CONF
The pathway is different, and the pathway is where the
controls are inserted.
NOTE CONF
So if you abstract away all the differences in the
pathway and you begin to treat all these three scenarios
NOTE CONF
as the same scenario, your controls are going to be
wrong.
NOTE CONF
They won't be fitting the pathway.
Which is why whenever we do risks, risk assessments, we
NOTE CONF
always insist that the asset and the threat and the
vulnerability, the combination of these is unique, always, always, always,
NOTE CONF
right?
And you go into as much detail as possible to
NOTE CONF
make sure they're unique.
So when you put in the controls, the controls are
NOTE CONF
fitting the actual scenario and not the generic asset and
the generic threat.
NOTE CONF
Yeah.
How important For us to talk about technical classes to
NOTE CONF
the data expert.
And those are talks that are there in the textbook.
NOTE CONF
So we need that.
that You can.
NOTE CONF
We will never ask you a question that requires you
to know the textbook as opposed to the slides.
NOTE CONF
Everything comes from the slides or from the online materials,
um, and you can use the textbook knowledge to add
NOTE CONF
to it, but we will never ask you something that's
only in the textbook.
NOTE CONF
Yeah.
OK, so, Consider two experienced chief information security officers.
NOTE CONF
One of them both implement a program of security controls.
One uses a risk assessment to inform what controls to
NOTE CONF
use, their decisions, and the other uses a compliance checklist
that is based on an international standard.
NOTE CONF
Which practice is better?
I really want to put this on the exam.
NOTE CONF
It really summarizes a lot of the, you know, A
lot of the deep profound ideas in this subject.
NOTE CONF
One uses a risk assessment, one uses a compliance checklist.
Sorry, yeah, um, I would assume the international standard because
NOTE CONF
it's been approved by many people and it's, I would
assume.
NOTE CONF
that So, I would assume that it's uh the international
standard because it's been tested and approved.
NOTE CONF
OK, one opinion, yes.
It depends upon what.
NOTE CONF
CPR.
And what is their strate?
NOTE CONF
So it depends on what they're trying to secure, what's
the strategy and what they're trying to implement, in what
NOTE CONF
case would you use what?
Probably for the first uh organization if they are trying
NOTE CONF
to make better decisions like I'm not really sure which.
It depends.
NOTE CONF
So context dependent is the answer, but not sure what
the contexts are, yes.
NOTE CONF
I think the question One come see here.
Sorry, the one is in.
NOTE CONF
So not only the, so the compliance is more general.
It could be applied everywhere and it could be also
NOTE CONF
applied in the risk assessment response following that.
But with risk assessment, it could be more tailored based
NOTE CONF
on the more tailored based on their context as opposed
to compliance.
NOTE CONF
So we have the two views.
These are the two sides of the argument, right?
NOTE CONF
One is compliance is, you know, international, international standard has
been tested, very, you know, consensus on what these things
NOTE CONF
are that you need to do.
And the other one is, but it's context, you know,
NOTE CONF
it's context dependent.
And in order to get a tailored cyber defense program,
NOTE CONF
you need to be looking at your specific risks.
So, which one is best?
NOTE CONF
It's a bit of a trick question, right?
Most organizations are doing both.
NOTE CONF
Yes.
Yeah, most organizations are doing both, um, but One of
NOTE CONF
them is highly problematic.
Right.
NOTE CONF
Not because it's a bad practice, but because it encourages
you to think wrongly about security.
NOTE CONF
Which of the two has a very bad impact on
the security mindset?
NOTE CONF
The, the 2nd 1, the 2nd 1, right?
The compliance.
NOTE CONF
Why?
It can be Can be outdated, yeah, but your risk
NOTE CONF
assessment can get outdated too, right?
Why is compliance so problematic?
NOTE CONF
Yes, because someone will use the compliance checklist and will
not think about like.
NOTE CONF
and get out.
they have Yeah, or they will just use the, yeah,
NOTE CONF
yes, yes.
So was there another point?
NOTE CONF
I think the compliance checklist consists of a, uh, set
rules and set logic that has to be picked up
NOTE CONF
by a person, and I think that covers the entire
risk scenario, whichever the which wherever the risk can be
NOTE CONF
possible.
Yeah, absolutely.
NOTE CONF
So let me, because we don't have unlimited time, um,
just quickly say a couple of things about this.
NOTE CONF
The biggest danger is the compliance mindset, which is, if
I tick these boxes and I do what the compliance
NOTE CONF
checklist tells me to do, I can go back to
sleep and do my regular business.
NOTE CONF
OK.
Compliance mindset encourages you to think that security is a
NOTE CONF
tick list.
If you achieve, if you can tick these boxes, you
NOTE CONF
are secure.
And that could not be further from the truth.
NOTE CONF
You could be compliant to every international standard, and you
could still get penetrated.
NOTE CONF
OK.
So, security.
NOTE CONF
Is defense.
Defense is constant.
NOTE CONF
It's vigilance.
It's knowing what's happening in your environment.
NOTE CONF
It's all the threat actors that are coming into your
environment.
NOTE CONF
It's noticing what is going on.
Being vigilant about what's happening and putting in controls, constantly
NOTE CONF
putting in new controls and testing old ones, that mentality
of being vigilant is exactly what compliance pushes you against.
NOTE CONF
It tells you don't worry about being vigilant.
Just tick these boxes, we're good.
NOTE CONF
Now those who believe in compliance will say, no, no,
no, no, no, no, you misunderstand.
NOTE CONF
This is not compliance is like the floor.
It's the minimum.
NOTE CONF
We're not telling you this is all you can do.
We're just saying everybody, if we didn't have compliance, then
NOTE CONF
across the nation there would be no minimum standard.
Some companies will put in a lot of money and
NOTE CONF
have good security, but a lot of companies will have
nothing.
NOTE CONF
So the government needs to put in a minimum standard
across the whole country, so at least there is some
NOTE CONF
level of security across the board and no big gaps.
And that logic is true.
NOTE CONF
It makes sense if you think of it that way.
The problem, of course, is that private organizations, cyber is
NOTE CONF
what for them.
A cost.
NOTE CONF
And so when they say what is the minimum investment
I need to put in to to deal with cyber,
NOTE CONF
they look for what to tell them what that minimum
investment is.
NOTE CONF
Compliance.
So their attitude, the attitude of the board of directors
NOTE CONF
and CEO is Compliance is the bar that we are
going to Set as our expenditure, you know, investment.
NOTE CONF
That's what we're going to invest in.
We're just going to reach compliance because it's a cost,
NOTE CONF
and we have to minimize cost.
That is the problem with compliance, right?
NOTE CONF
The people who come up with compliance have all these
grandiose ideas about how it should be used.
NOTE CONF
But when it gets pulled into the private enterprise market,
it gets treated as this is good enough.
NOTE CONF
Right.
Anything more, we get hacked above that, we've got insurance,
NOTE CONF
or we will write it off, but we're not spending
any more than what is the minimum, and the minimum
NOTE CONF
is set by compliance.
That is the grave danger with compliance.
NOTE CONF
It teaches you to go to sleep.
It teaches you that if you tick a set of
NOTE CONF
boxes, then that's good enough.
Now it's not saying that these might not be that
NOTE CONF
the controls in the boxes are not helpful.
I'm not saying that.
NOTE CONF
I'm saying that at a controlled operational level there may
be fantastic advice, but The mindset, the strategy cannot be
NOTE CONF
go to sleep, tick the boxes, go to sleep.
It's got to be be vigilant, know what's going on,
NOTE CONF
know who your threat actors are, build your defense, test
your defense, right?
NOTE CONF
And your best, best example here is nobody in the
army, you don't fight wars in the army using compliance,
NOTE CONF
right?
The Armies don't go to war with compliance tick lists.
NOTE CONF
Oh, if I have 1000 tanks and 10,000 of this
and 5000 of this, I'll win.
NOTE CONF
Great, right?
That's my minimum investment.
NOTE CONF
No, you go into battle knowing who your threat actor
is, war gaming scenarios, and teaching your soldiers leadership in
NOTE CONF
the heat of battle.
Right, that's what warfare is.
NOTE CONF
It's not compliance, and it's not even risk management, right?
Risk management is a civilian system.
NOTE CONF
It's not a military system.
In the military, they don't use risk management.
NOTE CONF
You cannot risk manage your way into, into victory, right?
You'll always end up in defeat if you think of
NOTE CONF
it as a risk management problem.
OK, we're in a civilian environment, so we think about
NOTE CONF
risk management.
OK, quickly, Policy Policy is a plan or a course
NOTE CONF
of action that conveys instructions from an organization's senior management
to those who make decisions.
NOTE CONF
So the important thing to know about policy, we're going
to talk a whole week, one whole week on policy,
NOTE CONF
is that it is your organization's opinion or position about
what to do.
NOTE CONF
Something and it's basically a set of rules.
There's enterprise rules and then they sort of get filtered
NOTE CONF
into practices and procedures and rules and guidelines and playbooks.
It's basically the leadership of the organization telling the employees
NOTE CONF
what the rules are.
That's policy.
NOTE CONF
Why do we need a policy?
Because you need to set rules.
NOTE CONF
If somebody does something unlawful, breaks the law, or violates
your organization's intent about something, you cannot, if you end
NOTE CONF
up in court, the first thing the judge is going
to ask you is what guidance have you given your
NOTE CONF
employees?
In other words, what's your policy?
NOTE CONF
Having a poor policy is not as bad as having
no policy.
NOTE CONF
No policy is unforgivable.
You will be in trouble if you do not have
NOTE CONF
a policy.
Poor policy, you can argue, well, you know, we can
NOTE CONF
improve it.
Um, what are the success factors for policy implementation when
NOTE CONF
somebody needs to make a decision, an employee, they need
to know what the policy is on that.
NOTE CONF
And normally it's very hard because the policy sits on
a shelf, it's 1000 pages long, and you can't find
NOTE CONF
the part of the policy that's relevant to what you
want to do.
NOTE CONF
So a good success factor is when an employee is
making a decision, the policy should pop up at that
NOTE CONF
point.
And how do we tell if it's working or not?
NOTE CONF
Easy.
If you want your employees to do A and they're
NOTE CONF
doing B, it's not working.
Right, if you wrote a policy, and you have no
NOTE CONF
idea what the culture is in the organization, then you
can be sure that people are not going to follow
NOTE CONF
the policy, right?
There's a very famous statement by a management consultant that
NOTE CONF
goes, culture, culture eats strategy for breakfast.
Right?
NOTE CONF
Or culture eats policy for breakfast, same thing in this
case, right?
NOTE CONF
And what it means is that you can tell people
to do, you know, something, you can, you can yell,
NOTE CONF
you can scream, you can do whatever you want, but
if it goes against the culture of the organization, they're
NOTE CONF
not going to follow it.
It doesn't matter, right?
NOTE CONF
So all the strategies in the world are not going
to help if the culture is against something.
NOTE CONF
So, for example, if we say, hey, do not write
your, your password on a yellow sticky on your computer.
NOTE CONF
But everybody's doing it, right?
When an employee comes in and goes, password, and he
NOTE CONF
sees sticky on every single computer with passwords on them,
what do you think they're going to do?
NOTE CONF
They're going to write your password on a sticky and
put it on the, yeah, it doesn't matter what the
NOTE CONF
policy says, right?
So it's important to, to know the difference between formal
NOTE CONF
policy, what's in the documents, and informal policy, which is
the behavior that we accept in the organizations.
NOTE CONF
Both are policy.
Right.
NOTE CONF
Policy, when, when people talk about policy, they usually mean
the document that's on the internet or on the shelf
NOTE CONF
that says policy on it.
But actually, that is not the real policy.
NOTE CONF
The policy is what everybody accepts is, you know, well,
what behavior is considered acceptable in the organization.
NOTE CONF
That is the policy.
If you don't stop behavior that's wrong, that means you
NOTE CONF
accept it, that means that is the policy.
Right?
NOTE CONF
And that's what happens in the court.
You can say, hey, we told employees, blah, blah, but
NOTE CONF
then the judge says to the employee, why did you
do it?
NOTE CONF
Everybody else does that.
Oh, OK, right.
NOTE CONF
Don't worry about what's in the document, that's what everybody
does, that's what the organization accepts, that's the policy.
NOTE CONF
OK.
So, strategy is a future course of action.
NOTE CONF
Using formal, informal and technological controls at a tactical and
operational level, and its job is to reduce the risk
NOTE CONF
exposure, right?
So what is strategy?
NOTE CONF
It's a set of choices.
What's a policy is a set of rules.
NOTE CONF
So for example, in the Horizon case, everybody's reading Horizon,
yes, yeah.
NOTE CONF
If Horizon, the company said, hey, we have all this
IP about the design of our supercars and we are
NOTE CONF
going to invest money in making sure that that IP
is on an air gapped computer that nobody who accesses
NOTE CONF
it can take away from it, that's a strategic decision.
Right, but saying that that IP if it's ever printed,
NOTE CONF
has this classification on it restricted, uh, and it's put
in this environment, etc.
NOTE CONF
etc.
those are rules, that's policy.
NOTE CONF
Right?
So policy is rules.
NOTE CONF
You can't do this, you cannot do that.
Strategy is choices.
NOTE CONF
We're going to invest in this, we're not going to
invest in that, right?
NOTE CONF
Strategy doesn't have to be financial, it can also be
security strategy, but we'll talk about that when we get
NOTE CONF
there.
Strategy is, again, decisions, it's prescriptive, and it usually starts
NOTE CONF
at the top of the organization and it goes downwards.
CETA, Security Education Training Awareness.
NOTE CONF
There's a difference between education, training and awareness.
And we'll talk about that when we get there, but
NOTE CONF
it is suggestive, not prescriptive.
We suggest to you how you can behave.
NOTE CONF
That's what awareness training and education does.
We don't prescribe how you behave, that's what policy does.
NOTE CONF
Policy says you can do A, you cannot do B,
but training and education awareness says, please consider doing this,
NOTE CONF
right?
Or please remember that hackers are in our vicinity, or
NOTE CONF
please remember, don't put, you know, please remember not to
write your password in in the wrong place.
NOTE CONF
That's your training and awareness.
Why does it fail?
NOTE CONF
It usually fails when you tell people to do things
that they don't want to do or are being told
NOTE CONF
not to do, so mixed messages is a problem.
Um, why do people have training?
NOTE CONF
Usually the right reasons is to tell, is to get
people to behave the right way, to change your culture,
NOTE CONF
cultural transformation.
But most training is done for compliance reasons, right?
NOTE CONF
So if you work in an organization and they've got
those online training modules that you flick through like mindlessly.
NOTE CONF
Every 3 months, yeah, you've got the training module open
and its information page, and you've got the questions open,
NOTE CONF
you're copying and pasting, which is what basically everybody's doing
in these useless online modules, right?
NOTE CONF
They're compliance driven, and that's the mindlessness of compliance, right?
Because nobody has free time to do security training.
NOTE CONF
And you're competing with the attention of an individual who
has 10,000 things to do.
NOTE CONF
Security training is the last thing they want to do,
and there are other other trainings they also have to
NOTE CONF
do.
So what are they going to do?
NOTE CONF
They are going to copy and paste and shut their
intellectual mind off, not learn anything, and just try to
NOTE CONF
get through it as soon as possible.
So, last slide.
NOTE CONF
There are 4 faces of a chief information security officer
that you should know about.
NOTE CONF
Sort of brings a lot of these things together, the
strategist, the advisor, the technologist, the guardian, right?
NOTE CONF
So every chief information security officer, in a sense, plays
these roles in some combination.
NOTE CONF
The technologists, their job is to assess and implement security
technologies and build standards and standards to build capability.
NOTE CONF
So this is a very technical role and traditionally it
has been a significant part of the CISO's job is
NOTE CONF
the technology part of it.
Then you've got the guardian role, which is to protect
NOTE CONF
business assets by understanding what the threat landscape is and
what the assets are and to protect the assets from
NOTE CONF
the threats.
And that is considered also to be considered considerable part
NOTE CONF
of the role, assumed to be, but my, I personally
think that they don't do much of it or they
NOTE CONF
don't think much about it, but that is considered to
be a big part of the role.
NOTE CONF
And then you've got two others.
The strategist, the person who drives businesses cyber risk strategy,
NOTE CONF
the alignment between what the business wants to do and
what security needs to do.
NOTE CONF
Right, so dealing with the leadership of the organization, placing
security in the business context, explaining to the board of
NOTE CONF
directors what security initiatives are in place, that's the strategist.
And then you've got the advisor.
NOTE CONF
Which is to evangelize, to go across the organization and
preach to all the other parts of the organization why
NOTE CONF
security is important, even though you don't have jurisdiction over
them.
NOTE CONF
Now, What's interesting You see the current and desired.
When Deloitte did this, this study about 10 years ago,
NOTE CONF
they, they Collected some metrics that suggest to them that
the what you see in current is what people's job
NOTE CONF
was when they were interviewed at that point.
What you see as desired is what they think their
NOTE CONF
job should be.
So in most of these, they wanted to be doing
NOTE CONF
more advisory work, more telling people about security, but they
seemed to be stuck in.
NOTE CONF
Guardian and technology work which is stuck in the technology
vertical, not being able to get out of the technology
NOTE CONF
domain, not being able to talk to the rest of
the organization, not being able to engage with the leadership
NOTE CONF
of the organization.
So you see the same problems that we were talking
NOTE CONF
about earlier on in the first week.
We see that everywhere we go, in every survey, every,
NOTE CONF
you know, metrics-based pictorial, the same story.
The SISOs are stuck.
NOTE CONF
They don't want to be stuck, but everybody thinks that
the role of the CISO is technical, and they don't
NOTE CONF
engage at the strategic level, and they don't engage horizontally
across the organization.
NOTE CONF
Yeah.
And I don't think in the last You know, 10
NOTE CONF
years, much has changed, at least not in this part
of the world where still sizeOs are very technical.
NOTE CONF
Now, what's interesting though, one thing that we haven't said,
got a few more minutes, is that this mix depends
NOTE CONF
on what kind of organization you're working in, right?
So if you're working in an airport, which of these
NOTE CONF
roles do you think is going to be the most
important role?
NOTE CONF
If you're the CIO of Melbourne Airport, which of these
roles?
NOTE CONF
You You think Guardian?
That's one possibility.
NOTE CONF
I would think advisor.
Why?
NOTE CONF
Because the airport is very flat organizational structure.
You've got baggage handlers, you've got airline ticket people, you've
NOTE CONF
got all the psychologists sitting behind those windows that you
can't see who are watching you when you're queuing.
NOTE CONF
You've got the security teams that sit at the top
of the airport.
NOTE CONF
of those teams, they are like separate.
It's not a pyramid vertical structure.
NOTE CONF
It's flat, which means if you're a sIO, you have
to cut across all these different teams.
NOTE CONF
You have no jurisdiction on them.
You're an advisor most of the time.
NOTE CONF
You don't have control.
What, which of these would be most important if you
NOTE CONF
were a size of a bank Sorry, guardian, yeah, yeah,
maybe guardian, depending on the size of the bank, technologist,
NOTE CONF
guardian, depending, yeah, but not so much advisor.
You're stuck in your vertical strategist maybe depending on the
NOTE CONF
size of the bank and the profile of the bank.
How about a um How about a government agency?
NOTE CONF
Like human services, right?
Centrelink.
NOTE CONF
What do you think?
Sorry, between.
NOTE CONF
Between strategies and technologies, I would be, yeah, it could
be.
NOTE CONF
Centrelink is very underfunded.
Right, it could be that there's always these technology issues
NOTE CONF
that are popping up.
But you would think in ideal circumstance that it would
NOTE CONF
be advisor, because again, Centrelink has a lot of different
teams, right?
NOTE CONF
Or strategist, maybe, but maybe it's not strategist because it's
not in order to be a strategist, you have to
NOTE CONF
have leadership, clear leadership in the firm that you can
engage with.
NOTE CONF
So you're talking strategy.
Otherwise, it's going to be Technologist, or advisor, if you
NOTE CONF
have to cut across a lot of, right?
So for example, if you're a health, health uh tech,
NOTE CONF
or um hospital, you would definitely be cutting across a
lot of different teams, right, with very little vertical.
NOTE CONF
So that means you would most likely be an advisor
and a technologist, right?
NOTE CONF
Hospitals are very underfunded.
Yeah.
NOTE CONF
The point though, what I'm trying to do, the last
point I'm gonna make is the mix depends on the
NOTE CONF
organization.
So there is a fit question, fit between the CISO
NOTE CONF
and the organization they're working for, because the threat environment,
the asset landscape is different.
NOTE CONF
from organization to organization, right?
If you take away one thing, it's the scio fits
NOTE CONF
the organization.
And that means the landscape, but also means how young
NOTE CONF
or old or mature the organization is.
The same size.
NOTE CONF
So in the 1st 5 years of an organization is
not going to work for the next 5 years or
NOTE CONF
the next 5 years after that, right?
When the organizations become mature, they need a different sizeO.
NOTE CONF
When they're starting up, they need a different size.
There's a fit between the SISO and the organization.
NOTE CONF
OK, see you next week.
Wait, wait, hold on.
NOTE CONF
I'll turn this off.
recorded OK, can we do like a 15 hour presentation?
NOTE CONF
What does that mean?
What do you mean?
NOTE CONF
You can do an activity if it is part of
your innovation, right?
NOTE CONF
Yeah, you're talking about, you're talking about the project, right?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, for week week 5 week
NOTE CONF
6, so you have to pitch an innovation, a solution
to a problem, right?
NOTE CONF
So if your problem requires you to demonstrate the solution,
sure.
NOTE CONF
Right, so, so I need to make it with the
innovation, of course this is, this is what you're pitching,
NOTE CONF
yeah, yeah, because one of the rubrics and you need
to make it more interactive and something like this, yeah,
NOTE CONF
but interactive can mean different things if you're presenting a
solution to a problem, then that could mean.
NOTE CONF
You know, whatever it could be this is the map
or this is the framework that I'm presenting or it
NOTE CONF
could be, hey, this is the problem.
People behave like this.
NOTE CONF
OK, you and you, let's demonstrate, you know, the behavior,
and then this is our solution and then the changes
NOTE CONF
the behavior.
I mean, yeah, you could do that.
NOTE CONF
It depends, you know.
OK, thank you.
NOTE CONF
Yes.
I think that I noticed that some policy can be
NOTE CONF
as well some can be strap can be what strap
strap and to lead to risk for I don't know
NOTE CONF
strip what strap strap mean spell it for me, yeah,
spell it, what is the word?
NOTE CONF
No, no, no, no, it's, it can be a risk
for.
NOTE CONF
Policies can be a risk.
Yes.
NOTE CONF
Oh, you said, OK, yeah, yeah.
No, no, OK.
NOTE CONF
A policy can be, if it's very specific about what
the organization does, if it gets leaked, it can become
NOTE CONF
a problem because people will realize what the policy is.
And and some conflict policy and it doesn't cover every
NOTE CONF
situation for the company and it also can be the
risk.
NOTE CONF
That's right.
If the policy gets analyzed and the organization has not
NOTE CONF
given guidance on something important.
Got it.
NOTE CONF
Thank you so much.
I was asking you in the email related to the
NOTE CONF
innovation you say that we need to add something on
top of maybe we find some way in the research
NOTE CONF
paper or like in the existing way that the page,
but I want to ask is there's in the category
NOTE CONF
of this.
that we need to give you your approach is actually
NOTE CONF
approach is different with the solution.
What do you mean by approach, so for example, if
NOTE CONF
I'm saying look, the problem is policy doesn't cover blah
blah blah.
NOTE CONF
You say, OK, my approach is I'm going to first
figure out what my culture as an organization.
NOTE CONF
I'm going to survey the people, then I'm going to
do on a focus group, and I find out what
NOTE CONF
is the problem.
Why aren't people obeying the leadership?
NOTE CONF
Then I'll write a policy.
Then I'll test the policy.
NOTE CONF
That approach, yeah, go.
You need to show us where did you get this
NOTE CONF
from.
Got it.
NOTE CONF
OK, thank you.
I mean, I know you said like.
NOTE CONF
Yeah, you just said 6 of us, but I just
want to.
NOTE CONF
No, listen to the 2.
No, no, no, I've, I've said very clearly that not
NOTE CONF
everybody has to present it.
You can choose your best.
NOTE CONF
And my next question is when you're talking about, uh,
the assessments, can't you like do a risk assessment and
NOTE CONF
create aliance checklist based on that?
I know he was following the international compliance checklist, but,
NOTE CONF
uh, like if you're talking about tailored compliance checklist.
tailored to that.
NOTE CONF
Yeah, but an internal, an internal risk of being contradicted
is not a compliance, right?
NOTE CONF
That's just your practice.
So it's, it's number it's compliance because when it's externally.
NOTE CONF